In this video, I'd like
在这段视频中 我想
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
to start talking about how to
讨论如何
multiply together two matrices.
将两个矩阵相乘
We'll start with a special case
我们将从矩阵相乘的
of that, of matrix vector
特例  向量相乘开始
multiplication -  multiplying a matrix together with a vector.
即 一个矩阵与一个向量相乘
Let's start with an example.
让我们从一个示例开始
Here is a matrix,
左边是一个矩阵
and here is a vector, and
右边是一个向量
let's say we want to
假设我们要
multiply together this matrix
将这个矩阵
with this vector, what's the result?
与这个向量相乘 结果会怎样呢？
Let me just work through this
我先快速计算出结果
example and then we
然后我们再
can step back and look at just what the steps were.
退回去 查看每一个步骤
It turns out the result of
很明显 相乘的结果
this multiplication process is going
将是
to be, itself, a vector.
一个向量
And I'm just going work
我先将这部分完成
with this first and later we'll
然后再来解释
come back and see just what I did here.
我刚刚是怎么做的
To get the first element of
要计算出结果向量的第一个元素
this vector I am going
我将会
to take these two numbers
取这两个数字
and multiply them with
并把他们
the first row of the
与矩阵的第一行相乘
matrix and add up the corresponding numbers.
然后把对应相乘的结果加起来
Take one multiplied by
取1乘以1
one, and take
同时取3
three and multiply it by
乘以
five, and that's
what, that's one plus fifteen so that gives me sixteen.
计算得到1和15 相加得16
I'm going to write sixteen here.
我将在这儿写上16
then for the second row,
要计算第二行
second element, I am
的第二个元素
going to take the second row
我需要将第二行
and multiply it by this vector,
与这个向量相乘
so I have four
所以我得到
times one, plus zero
4乘以1
times five, which is
加上0乘以5
equal to four, so you'll have four there.
结果等于4 因此在这里写上4
And finally for the last
对于最后一个元素
one I have two one times
我需要计算(2, 1) 乘以 (1, 5)
one five, so two
所以先计算2乘以1
by one, plus one
再加上
by 5, which is equal
1乘以5
to a 7, and
最后结果为7
so I get a 7 over there.
所以我在这儿写上7
It turns out that the
事实证明
results of multiplying that's
3x2的矩阵
a 3x2 matrix by a
和一个2x1的矩阵
2x1 matrix is also
即一个二维向量
just a two-dimensional vector.
相乘的结果
The result of this is
我们得到的
going to be a 3x1
将是一个3x1
matrix, so that's why
的矩阵
three by one 3x1
这个3x1的矩阵
matrix, in other words
就是这么得来的
a 3x1 matrix is just a three dimensional vector.
也就是一个三维向量
So I realize that I
我想
did that pretty quickly, and you're
我可能计算时做得很快
probably not sure that you can
你们并不一定能够
repeat this process yourself, but
自己重复这个过程
let's look in more detail
下面让我们更加仔细的看一下
at what just happened and what
刚刚我做了些什么以及一个向量
this process of multiplying a matrix by a vector looks like.
和一个矩阵相乘的计算过程是怎样的
Here's the details of how to
下面详细介绍了如何
multiply a matrix by a vector.
计算一个矩阵与一个向量相乘
Let's say I have a matrix A
假设这是一个矩阵A
and want to multiply it by
我希望将它乘以
a vector x. The
一个向量x
result is going to be some
结果记为
vector y. So the
向量y 所以
matrix A is a m
矩阵A是一个
by n dimensional matrix, so
mxn维矩阵
m rows and n columns and
有m行和n列
we are going to multiply that by a
我们让它与一个
n by 1 matrix, in other words an n dimensional vector.
nx1的矩阵相乘 换言之 一个n维向量
It turns out this
明显地
"n" here has to match this "n" here.
这里的两个n是相等的
In other words, the number of
也就是说
columns in this matrix, so
这个矩阵的列数
it's the number of n columns.
有n列
The number of columns here has
必须要与
to match the number of rows here.
另一个相乘矩阵的行数相同
It has to match the dimension of this vector.
即必须匹配这个向量的维数。
And the result of this product
这样相乘的结果
is going to be an n-dimensional
将会是一个n维
vector y.  Rows here.
向量y
"M" is going
“M”将与
to be equal to the number
矩阵A的行数
of rows in this matrix "A".
相同
So how do you actually compute this vector "Y"?
那么如何计算这个向量“Y”呢？
Well it turns out to compute
事实上
this vector "Y", the process
计算“Y”的过程可以分解为
is to get "Y""I", multiply "A's"
计算“Y”“I”的值
"I'th" row with the
让“A”的第I行元素
elements of the vector "X"
分别乘以向量“X”中的元素
and add them up.
并且相加
So here's what I mean.
就是这样子
In order to get the
为了得到
first element of "Y",
“Y”的第一个元素
that first number--whatever that turns
无论是多少
out to be--we're gonna take
我们将会
the first row of the
把矩阵“A”的
matrix "A" and multiply
第一行元素
them one at a time
每次同一个向量“X”的元素
with the elements of this vector "X".
相乘
So I take this first number
我取第一个数
multiply it by this first number.
与第一个数相乘
Then take the second number multiply it by this second number.
然后取第二个数同第二个数相乘
Take this third number whatever
取第三个数
that is, multiply it the third number
与第三个数相乘
and so on until you get to the end.
直到全部乘完
And I'm gonna add up the
最后 将这些相乘的结果
results of these products and the
加起来
result of paying that out is going to give us this first element of "Y".
这样我们就得到了“Y”的第一个元素
Then when we want to get
然后我们
the second element of "Y", let's say this element.
来计算“Y”的第二个元素
The way we do that is we
接下来我们
take the second row of
取A的第二行
A and we repeat the whole thing.
然后重复整个过程
So we take the second row
现在 我们取A的第二行
of A, and multiply it
将它
elements-wise, so the elements
与其他元素相乘
of X and add
也就是X的元素
up the results of the products
将结果相加
and that would give me the
这样我们就得到了
second element of Y. And
Y的第二个元素
you keep going to get and we
依次计算下去
going to take the third row
我们取A得第三行
of A, multiply element Ys
把元素Ys与
with the vector x,
向量x相乘
sum up the results and then
将结果加起来
I get the third element and so
然后得到第三个元素
on, until I get down
以此类推
to the last row like so, okay?
直到最后一行
So that's the procedure.
所以 上述就是具体步骤
Let's do one more example.
让我们再举一个例子
Here's the example:  So let's look at the dimensions.
在这个例子中 我们先看一下矩阵的维度
Here, this is a three
左边是一个
by four dimensional matrix.
3x4矩阵
This is a four-dimensional vector,
右边是一个四维向量
or a 4 x 1 matrix, and
也就是4x1矩阵
so the result of this, the
所以这样相乘的结果
result of this product is going
将是
to be a three-dimensional vector.
一个三维向量
Write, you know, the vector,
我们在写的时候要给这个向量
with room for three elements.
留三个元素的空间
Let's do the, let's carry out the products.
现在让我们一起来算一下
So for the first element, I'm
首先是第一个元素
going to take these four numbers
我将会取这四个数
and multiply them with the
并将它们与向量X相乘
vector X. So I have
所以我需要计算
1x1, plus 2x3,
1x1 加上2X3
plus 1x2, plus 5x1, which
加1X2 加5X1
is equal to - that's
等于
1+6, plus 2+6, which gives me 14.
1 +6 再加上2 +6 也就是14。
And then for the
然后计算
second element, I'm going
第二个元素 我要
to take this row now and
取这一行
multiply it with this vector  (0x1)+3.
然后与向量 (0X1)+3相乘
All right, so
我们将得到
0x1+  3x3 plus
0x1 + 3x3
0x2 plus 4x1,
0X2 + 4X1
which is equal to, let's
等于
see that's 9+4, which is 13.
9 +4 也就是13。
And finally, for the last
最后
element, I'm going to take
对最后一个元素
this last row, so I
我将取最后一行
have minus one times one.
所以我得到了-1x1
You have minus two, or really there's a plus next to a two I guess.
-2x3
Times three plus zero
加上0x2
times two plus zero times
加上0x1
one, and so that's
所以
going to be minus one minus
我们将得到-1和-6
six, which is going to make
相加得
this seven, and so that's vector seven.
Okay?
明白了？
So my final answer is this
所以我最后的答案是
vector fourteen, just to
一个向量 其中的元素为 14
write to that without the colors, fourteen,
我将不给这些字涂上颜色
thirteen, negative seven.
13 -7
And as promised, the
如前面说的
result here is a three by one matrix.
计算结果是一个3X1的矩阵
So that's how you multiply a matrix and a vector.
上述就是矩阵和向量相乘的方法
I know that a lot just
我知道
happened on this slide, so
这张幻灯片上内容很多
if you're not quite sure where all
如果你在看的过程中
these numbers went, you know,
不是很确定这些数字怎么来的
feel free to pause the video
你可以随时暂停视频
you know, and so take a
慢慢地
slow careful look at this
仔细琢磨
big calculation that we just
整个计算过程
did and try to make
尽量
sure that you understand the steps
确保自己理解了
of what just happened to get
得到14 13 11
us these numbers,fourteen, thirteen and eleven.
这些结果的每一个步骤
Finally, let me show you a neat trick.
最后 我将教你们一个小技巧。
Let's say we have
假设我
a set of four houses so 4
有四间房子
houses with 4 sizes like these.
这些房子有四种大小
And let's say I have a
我有一个
hypotheses for predicting what is
假设函数
the price of a house, and
用于预测房子的价格
let's say I want to compute,
我需要计算
you know, H of X for each of my 4 houses here.
四间房子的大小作为X值时 H的大小（即预测的房价）
It turns out there's neat way
这里有一种简单的方法
of posing this, applying this
可以同时
hypothesis to all of my houses at the same time.
计算四间房子的预测价格
It turns out there's a neat
我可以将它简单地
way to pose this as a
利用
Matrix Vector multiplication.
矩阵向量相乘的思想来计算
So, here's how I'm going to do it.
所以 对于这个问题我会这么计算
I am going to construct a matrix as follows.
首先我要构建一个
My matrix is going to be
如下所示的矩阵
1111 times, and I'm
元素是1111
going to write down the sizes
然后我把四个房子的大小
of my four houses here and
写在这儿
I'm going to construct a vector
我还需要构造一个向量
as well, And my
我的向量
vector is going to this
它将是一个
vector of two elements, that's
二维向量
minus 40 and 0.25.
即 40 和 0.25
That's these two co-efficients;
这是预测函数的两个系数
data 0 and data 1.
theta0 和 theta1
And what I am going
接下来
to do is to take matrix
我要做的就是
and that vector and multiply them
将我构造好的矩阵和向量相乘
together, that times is that multiplication symbol.
这是相乘符号
So what do I get?
我将得到??什么结果呢？
Well this is a
左边是一个
four by two matrix.
4X2 矩阵。
This is a two by one matrix.
右边是一个 2X1 矩阵
So the outcome is going
所以结果
to be a four by one
将是一个4X1向量
vector, all right.
对吧
So, let me,
所以 让我在幻灯片上写上
so this is
结果将是
going to be a 4 by
一个4X1的矩阵
1 matrix is the outcome or
输出结果也就是
really a four diminsonal vector,
一个四维向量
so let me write it as
让我来把它写出来
one of my four elements in my four real numbers here.
用四个实数表示我的四个元素
Now it turns out and so
事实上
this first element of this
结果的第一个元素
result, the way I
我的计算方式
am going to get that is, I
是
am going to take this and multiply it by the vector.
将这一行同我的向量相乘
And so this is going to
结果将是
be -40 x
-40x1
1 + 4.25 x 2104.
+ 4.25×2104。
By the way, on
顺便说一下
the earlier slides I was
在先前的幻灯片中
writing 1 x -40 and
我写的是 1x-40
2104 x 0.25, but
+ 2104x0.25
the order doesn't matter, right?
但是顺序无关紧要 对吧？
-40 x 1 is the same as 1 x -40.
-40×1 和 1×-40是一样的
And this first element, of course,
这第一个元素
is "H" applied to 2104.
就是当x为2104时的H值
So it's really the
因此
predicted price of my first house.
这是我的第一个房子的预测价格
Well, how about the second element?
那么 第二个元素呢？
Hope you can see
你应该已经想到了
where I am going to get the second element.
我要怎么计算第二个元素了
Right?
对吗？
I'm gonna take this and multiply it by my vector.
我要把这个乘以我的向量
And so that's gonna be
所以就是
-40 x 1 + 0.25 x 1416.
-40×1 + 0.25×1416
And so this is going be "H" of 1416.
这就是x为1416的“H”值。
Right?
理解了吗？
And so on for the
这是第三个
third and the fourth
和第四个
elements of this 4 x 1 vector.
后面就依次计算这个4X1矩阵的第三和第四个元素
And just there, right?
得出结果
This thing here that I
这里
just drew the green box around,
我画了绿色边框的部分
that's a real number, OK?
是一个实数 对吧？
That's a single real number,
它是一个实数
and this thing here that
这里
I drew the magenta box around--the
我画了洋红色边框的部分
purple, magenta color box
紫色 洋红色 边框
around--that's a real number, right?
是一个实数 对吧？
And so this thing on
所以右边
the right--this thing on the
最右边
right overall, this is a
就是一个
4 by 1 dimensional matrix, was a 4 dimensional vector.
4X1矩阵 是一个4维向量
And, the neat thing about
这个例子的一个小技巧是
this is that when you're
当你
actually implementing this in software--so
在程序中实现这个过程的时候
when you have four houses and
当你有四间房子
when you want to use your hypothesis
你想使用自己的预测函数
to predict the prices, predict the price "Y" of all of these four houses.
来预测房子的价格
What this means is that, you
完成这些工作
know, you can write this in one line of code.
你可以用一行代码搞定
When we talk about octave and
我们后面会谈到Octave
program languages later, you can
以及编程语言
actually, you'll actually write this in one line of code.
你可以只写一行代码就完成整个过程
You write prediction equals my,
你可以这样写
you know, data matrix times
prediction = data matrix * parameters
parameters, right?
对吧
Where data matrix is
数据矩阵是这一部分
this thing here, and parameters
参数
is this thing here, and this
是这一部分
times is a matrix vector multiplication.
这就是一个矩阵向量乘法
And if you just do this then
如果你这么做了
this variable prediction - sorry
这个变量prediction
for my bad handwriting - then
抱歉 我的字写得很潦草
just implement this one
只需要实现
line of code assuming you have
这一行代码
an appropriate library to do matrix vector multiplication.
如果你有一个做矩阵向量相乘的函数库的话
If you just do this,
如果你这样做的话
then prediction becomes this
右侧的prediction变量就会形成
4 by 1 dimensional vector, on
一个4维向量
the right, that just gives you all the predicted prices.
给你所有的预测价格。
And your alternative to doing
另一种计算方式是
this as a matrix vector multiplication
作为一种矩阵向量相乘的方式
would be to write eomething like
实际上就是一种
, you know, for I equals 1 to 4, right?
通过for循环 for 1 to 4 对吧？
And you have say a thousand houses
如果说你有一千间房子
it would be for I equals 1 to a thousand or whatever.
就将是 for 1 to 1000 或者别的任何数
And then you have to write a
然后如果i等于的话 你必须写一个
prediction, you know, if I equals.
有一个假设条件 I相等
and then do a bunch
然后需要做
more work over there and it
比矩阵向量相乘多得多的工作
turns out that When you
当你有
have a large number of houses,
大量的房子的时候
if you're trying to predict the prices
如果你试图预测
of not just four but maybe
不只是四座
of a thousand houses then
或许是一千座房子的时候
it turns out that when
事实证明
you implement this in the
当你使用矩阵向量相乘的方法时
computer, implementing it like this, in any of the various languages.
在计算机中 使用任何语言
This is not only true for
不仅仅是Octave
Octave, but for Supra Server
还有Supra Server Java Python
Java or Python, other high-level, other languages as well.
等高级语言 以及其他语言 都可以很快的实现
It turns out, that, by writing
事实证明
code in this style on the
像左边这样子写代码
left, it allows you to
不仅可以
not only simplify the
简化你的代码
code, because, now, you're just
现在你只需要
writing one line of code
写一行代码
rather than the form of a bunch of things inside.
而不是一堆代码
But, for subtle reasons, that we
而且 还有一个微妙的好处
will see later, it turns
我们后面将会了解到
out to be much more computationally
就是基于你所有的房子
efficient to make predictions
这样做计算效率将会更高
on all of the prices of
比你像右边那样
all of your houses doing it
用代码实现公式
the way on the left than the
的方式效率
way on the right than if you were to write your own formula.
将会高很多
I'll say more about this
我后面在讨论向量化的时候
later when we talk about
会详细地
vectorization, but, so, by
讨论这个问题
posing a prediction this way, you
所以 通过这种方式计算预测值
get not only a simpler piece
不仅代码更加简洁
of code, but a more efficient one.
而且效率更高
So, that's it for
以上就是矩阵向量相乘的全部内容
matrix vector multiplication and we'll
我们在后面
make good use of these sorts
在其他模型中
of operations as we develop
计算实例的回归的时候
the living regression in other models further.
将会有效地利用到这一讲的内容
But, in the next video we're
在接下来的视频中
going to take this and generalize this
我将会从特殊到一般
to the case of matrix matrix multiplication.
讲讲矩阵与矩阵相乘的情况